<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Jalves Nicacio</title>
    <link>https://jalvesnicacio.github.io/en/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Jalves Nicacio</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://jalvesnicacio.github.io/en/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the Web Accessibility Problem?</title>
      <link>https://jalvesnicacio.github.io/en/post/accessibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalvesnicacio.github.io/en/post/accessibility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-ever-evolving-web&#34;&gt;The Ever-Evolving Web&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet, with its myriad components like email, websites, servers, and browsers, can be bewildering, even for those who have grown up in the digital age. Its constant evolution since inception has dramatically transformed how we connect, share information, solve problems, study, or entertain ourselves. Increasingly, the Web is replacing traditional services such as mail and telephony, underscoring its significance in our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;highlighting-the-inaccessibility-issue&#34;&gt;Highlighting the Inaccessibility Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite its vast potential, the Web&amp;rsquo;s accessibility issues often go unnoticed, affecting individuals who could benefit from its services. Consider the following scenarios highlighting the diverse challenges faced by users:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&amp;rsquo;s Dilemma:&lt;/strong&gt; Colorblindness makes it impossible for John to distinguish discounted prices highlighted in red on an online shopping site, complicating his shopping experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sandra&amp;rsquo;s Struggle:&lt;/strong&gt; With Down syndrome, Sandra finds navigating the overwhelming options on a supermarket website difficult, exacerbating her challenges with reading and mathematical concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Henry&amp;rsquo;s Hope:&lt;/strong&gt; Blindness doesn&amp;rsquo;t stop Henry from exploring the Web with a screen reader, but not all sites are accessible, dampening his newfound independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These examples underline a stark reality: when we limit access to web services and information, we contribute to a broader issue of social and digital exclusion. Web systems simplify life for many, but for people with disabilities, they are essential tools that enable tasks that might otherwise be daunting or impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;towards-a-more-accessible-web&#34;&gt;Towards a More Accessible Web&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What steps can we take to ensure web pages and systems are accessible to individuals with disabilities? Future articles will delve into essential concepts, strategies, and practices to design and adapt websites for accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-importance-of-web-accessibility&#34;&gt;The Importance of Web Accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web accessibility should be a priority for everyone publishing content online, regardless of their familiarity with IT and web technologies. Understanding accessibility&amp;rsquo;s critical aspects, performing usability and accessibility tests, and promoting awareness are pivotal. IT professionals, marketers, SEO managers, programmers, webmasters, designers, usability consultants, and students must learn to ensure their digital offerings are accessible to all, including those with temporary or permanent disabilities. Building with accessibility in mind from the start is easier and more inclusive than retrofitting websites later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Support for citations from GitHub repositories.</title>
      <link>https://jalvesnicacio.github.io/en/post/github-citations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jalvesnicacio.github.io/en/post/github-citations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-you-make-it-easier-for-others-to-cite-your-work&#34;&gt;How do you make it easier for others to cite your work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In academic work, we often develop prototypes or make data visualizations available through repositories. One way we make these research artifacts available is through the GitHub platform, which allows us not only to make software, prototypes, or data publicly available, but also to control their versioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when we write an article and want to reference a GitHub repository, it can be a bit difficult to know how best to reference these repositories. With this in mind, Github has recently created a way to officially support citations to the data or code repository. This new feature, developed by GitHub, allows researchers and academics to inform the community and interested parties on how to properly cite their repositories, especially in scientific articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do so, researchers must add a new file to their repository: CITATION.cff. According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.blog/2021-08-19-enhanced-support-citations-github/&#34;&gt;Arfon Smith&lt;/a&gt;, a member of the Github team, the information in this file is used to create convenient APA or BibTeX-style citation links that can be referenced by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enable this feature in your repository, you can simply create a file named CITATION.cff in your repository. Use the example below as a template for your file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;cff-version: 1.2.0
message: &amp;#34;If you use this software, please cite it as below.&amp;#34;
authors:
  - family-names: Druskat
    given-names: Stephan
    orcid: https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4925-7248
title: &amp;#34;My Research Software&amp;#34;
version: 2.0.4
doi: 10.5281/zenodo.1234
date-released: 2021-08-11
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can also use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://citation-file-format.github.io/cff-initializer-javascript/&#34;&gt;cffinit&lt;/a&gt; website to fill in your citation file information. You can get more information about the cff file format on this page: &lt;a href=&#34;https://citation-file-format.github.io/&#34;&gt;What is a CITATION.cff file?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;cffinit-screen.png&#34; alt=&#34;Cffinit website screenshot&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
